Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ע"ג, Ayin Gimmel, 73,
and let's get started. So we picked up at the very bottom
of ע"ב עמוד ב, Ayin Bais Amud Bais,
actually no, I'm sorry, the very top of ע"ג עמוד א, Ayin
Gimmel Amud Alef, 73a. כמאן כרבי מאיר? Keman k'Rebbi Meir? So the
גמרא Gemara is talking about there's a fascinating debate in the משנה,
Mishnah, at least fascinating for us who like the גמרא, Gemara, about
whether the limb that is stuck out from the womb when the
animal is שחט, shachated, is that considered like a נבילה neveilah or
like a טריפה? treifah? Is it like it never got a שחיטה,
shechitah, which makes it a נבילה, neveilah, or got a שחיטה shechitah
that didn't work, which makes it like a טריפה? treifah? That it
was somehow considered, you know, the שחיטה shechitah did apply, did work,
because it was still considered part of the animal, it just didn't
work for it because it was out of the womb. So one
way of thinking about that is was it still considered to be
גופא gufa or not גופא, gufa, part of the animal or not
part of the animal, or perhaps everybody agrees it's not גופא gufa
but still says the שחיטה shechitah relates to it. Anyway, that's the
question, whether it was a נבילה neveilah or טריפה. treifah. The biggest
difference being whether that causes טומאה. tumah. So according to רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir that it's a נבילה neveilah and it causes טומאה, tumah,
he says that it makes the rest of the fetus טמא. tamei.
The question then is, that but it's not touching the rest of
the fetus, it's only touching on the non-revealed surface, which is the
בית הסתרים, beis hastarim, right, but it's touching, but there's no exposed
surface that it's touching. So the גמרא Gemara says, well maybe רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir is going according to his reasoning that since this
limb is fit to be cut because you wouldn't want to eat
it anyway because it's not kosher, you're only going to eat the
rest, so it's sort of in the fit to be cut, it's
expected to be cut off. Therefore it's like it's cut off and
it's like there's already an exposed surface. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara is going to analyze this. Let's take a look. Top of
ע"ג עמוד א. Ayin Gimmel Amud Alef. כמאן? Keman? So who are
you saying this is going like, that something that's fit to be
cut is like it's cut? כרבי מאיר. K'Rebbi Meir. Like רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, which is fine because the משנה Mishnah was רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir anyway, this
opinion. דתנן, De-tenan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, a different משנה
Mishnah in מקואות: Mikvaos: כל ידות הכלים, Kol yadot hakelim, all handles
of vessels שאין ארוכות she-ein arukot that are long, imagine you have
like a very long handle of a frying pan or
something, ועתיד לקצצן ve-asid lekattetzan but you are going to cut them
off. Okay, why are you going to cut them off? Because maybe
it's too long or something. You made a vessel, you got a
long handle, but you decide it's too long. Now the vessel is
טמא. tamei. So do you have to put the whole handle in
the מקוה? mikvah? So the משנה Mishnah says: מטביל עד מקום מדה.
Matbil ad mekom middah. You do a טבילה tvilah until the measure,
meaning until where you're going to cut off. So imagine you have
a super long handle on your frying pan and it's way too
long for you, so you're planning on cutting it off, maybe it
makes more sense if you think of it as wood than as
metal, doesn't matter. Anyway, so you don't have to dump the whole
thing in the מקוה, mikvah, maybe it doesn't even all fit in
the מקוה, mikvah, you only have to put in the מקוה mikvah
until the part of the handle that you're going to keep. Okay,
that's the first opinion. In this case, it's דבי רבי מאיר, divei
Rebbi Meir, but some just have that as the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, but the implication being that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-chachamim omrim, even although outside רבי
יהודה אומר: Rebbi Yehuda omer: עד שיטביל את כולו. Ad she-yatvil es
kulo. You have to put it all in the מקוה. mikvah. So
the question here is exactly this. You have to put the whole
vessel in the מקוה. mikvah. What is considered to be the whole
vessel? So according to the first opinion, if you're about planning on
cutting it off, it's no longer part of the vessel. And that's
כל העומד לחתוך כחתוך דמי. kol ha-omed lachatoch ke-chatuach dami.
Something that is standing to be cut off, you are planning on
cutting it off, it's like it's already cut off, it's no longer
part of the vessel. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says as long as
it's still attached, it's still attached, I don't look like what you're
planning on doing with it. And therefore you have to put the
whole thing in the מקוה. mikvah. So the ability here, that that's
a קולא, kulah, leniency, it lets you put only part of the
vessel in the מקוה, mikvah, but it also can be a stringency
in our case with the limb that's טמא tamei and it's connected
to the fetus that's not טמא. tamei. If you look at it
as though it's already cut, then it's like it has already an
exposed surface and like the surfaces are touching. So we're there saying
that רבי Rebbi that that works within רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who
sees things that are standing to be cut as if they are
cut. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say maybe it's
not even limited to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. אפילו תימא רבנן. Afilu
teima rabbanan. Maybe even the rabbis would agree in the case of
the fetus and the limb. חיבורי אוכלין כמאן דמפרש דמי ונגעי בהדדי.
Chibburei ochlin ke-man de-mifrash dami ve-nagei behadadi. So it says things that
are food is easier to see as something that is in the
process of being cut than things like vessels. Okay, because what do
you do with food? You cut it up and you eat it.
Okay, so since here you've got this dead fetus and a dead
limb,
and it's initially
food, well, okay, but things that could, you know, you're going to
be eating the fetus, and so these are types of food, you
know, things that are and what are you going to do with
the limb? You'll probably throw it to the dogs. So things that
are basically for consumption, in the process of consuming they get destroyed
anyway, and usually prior to that they get cut up. So there,
they don't have as much if you would sort of as
like integrity as an item because you sort of see the whole
food is in the process of being destroyed and in the process
of cut up. So it's easier to see the limb as if
it were already detached from the fetus, and even the rabbis might
agree that that allows it to be considered touching the fetus and
transmitting טומאה, tumah, whereas by a vessel that has natural more... or
unity and until you actually detach it it is considered to be
whole. So even the רבנן rabbis here could agree that it is
as if it is already detached. Let's just read through the two
dots and then I'll take questions and I want to make a
comment as well. So the גמרא Gemara says: בשלמא לעולא היינו דקתני
חתכה. Bishlama le'Ulla haynu dekateni chatacha. So now we have two explanations
of how the limb causes טומאה tumah to the thing if it's
not an exposed surface. One is in the process of cutting it
off, then you create the exposed surface and in that process the
surfaces will touch. So right now it doesn't cause טומאה tumah but
when you cut it off it will create it. That's what we
said yesterday. Right, when you cut it off it'll expose the surface
and then they'll touch. Now we've said even if you haven't cut
it off yet, the fact that it's about to be cut off
makes it as if that's already happened. So now the גמרא Gemara
says according to עולא, Ulla, which was yesterday's opinion, thank you so
much, according to עולא, Ulla, which is yesterday's opinion, that makes sense.
היינו דקתני חתכה. haynu dekateni chatacha. The משנה Mishnah says you cut
it and then it's מטמא. metamei. You cut off the limb, it
causes טומאה. tumah. So according to עולא Ulla it's only once you
cut off the limb and you expose the surface and then they
touch in the process of being separated.
אלא לרבינא, Ela le-Ravina, רבינא Ravina which is the opinion we just
dealt with now that it's as if it's already cut, מאי חתכה?
mai chatacha? Why do you have to say if you cut it
off? Even before cutting it it transmits the טומאה. tumah. So גמרא
Gemara says, no, איידי דתני רישא חתכה. Aidi detani reisha chatacha. Since
the first part of the משנה, Mishnah, remember the first part said
that you cut off the limb before you shechted the mother. So
there it spoke about cutting it off, so תנא נמי סיפא חתכה
tana nami seifa chatacha gives it in the last case. But you're
actually right. So the difference between the two opinions is the one
that says you're right, as long as it's not cut, the surface
is not exposed, it can't transmit. It's a little ironic, right? The
whole thing is so naturally one unity, but it doesn't communicate טומאה
tumah because the whole idea almost of communicating טומאה tumah is this
thing comes in contact with that thing and transmits its טומאה. tumah.
When it's all one big thing, no טומאה tumah is transmitted. That's
actually a little ironic, but you sort of hear that. So therefore,
until you cut it off, no טומאה tumah will be transmitted. When
you cut it off and you expose the surface and then the
surfaces touch, then only that is when it is transmitted. Whereas the
other opinion says no, the fact that that's going to happen, it's
like it's already happened and you view it as if it's already
cut and as if they're touching and therefore that's how the טומאה
tumah is transmitted. So those are the two opinions about even if
we admit that the limb is טמא, tamei, how it transmits the
טומאה. tumah. I want to make one final comment and then Michael
had a question, which is, תוספות Tosafot has the following question. תוספות
Tosafot says: I understand in the case of this vessel with the
long sort of handle, that you don't have to put the whole
thing in the מקוה mikveh if you look at the rest of
it as if it's already cut off. But תוספות Tosafot says: let
it be cut off. It's cut off and it's touching, right? That's
what we had in our case. It's as if the limb was
cut off and it's touching and therefore transmits טומאה. tumah. Well, what
would you have? If you had a long handle or you had
a handle that was not long, that was short, and something else
that was not part of it was touching it and attached to
it, and sort of physically smacked against it and you put it
in the מקוה. mikveh. Would it work? You put the whole vessel
in the מקוה mikveh but there's a problem. What's the problem?
חציצה. Chatzitzah. Some of it is being covered. So let the remainder
of the handle not be considered the same handle so you don't
have to put it in the מקוה. mikveh. Why doesn't it create
a problem that it's covering the virtual exposed surface? So can you
have it both ways? Can you say because the handle is fit
to be cut off it doesn't have to go in the מקוה,
mikveh, but because the surface where you would make the cut is
not yet exposed, the surface doesn't have to touch the water? Can
you have that both ways? So תוספות Tosafot doesn't think you can
have it both ways and תוספות Tosafot makes this a very unusual
case. He says the handle we're talking about here is not a
wood handle, it's basically like a chain link handle. Okay? So if
it's a chain link handle and you imagine that you were to
cut off part of the link, it still, the rest of it
is still water can get to what remains even while it's still
attached because they're just like this. So water can still get on
all of the links. So that's a very ingenious way תוספות Tosafot
solves this problem, but it raises an interesting question: when you say
something is as if it already occurred, how far do you go
with the as-if? As-if, so it's enough that you don't have to
put the rest of the handle in the מקוה, mikveh, but as-if
so much that you consider it as though there's an exposed surface
that's now being covered and that's not getting water on it? So
that is the question that תוספות Tosafot raises. You had a question?
So according to the opinion that says it's already happened so you
have to dip the whole thing, is it because part of it
is not exposed, it'll kind of communicate טומאה tumah to the rest
of the vessel?
No, because a vessel if it is a,
no, that's not the concern. That's an interesting way of framing it,
but you could have a case where that's not true. Meaning if
the vessel itself were a,
were ראשון, rishon, which is a standard case, then it doesn't
matter. A vessel can only be a ראשון, rishon, it can't be
a שני. sheni. So if only half of the vessel were טהור
tahor and half were טמא, tamei, it would, it would not communicate
טומאה tumah to itself because it would not be able to become.
And why can't you leave part of it out? Like what's the
problem?
Because of, because the הלכה halacha is, right, the assumption here is
that you have to put independent of concerns of חציצה, chatzitza, you
have to put the whole item into, you know, into the מקווה.
mikvah. Right, you know, the whole unit had to go, for example,
I'll give you an example. Why is a person can I not
go into a מקווה mikvah and first I'll go up to my
waist and then I'll go, you know, and or and then I'll
go head first and only the second half? Will that work? So
there's a principle of אין טבילה לחצאין, ein tvilah l'chatzain, right, whatever
that unit is, it has to all go into the מקווה. mikvah.
It's not because half of me is מטמא metamei the other half.
Okay, but you can't be מטהר metaher half of something, you have
to be מטהר metaher as a whole thing.
Okay, so when we're doing יד ידיים, yad yadayim, is it because
conceptually those things are hands are separate from our body?
Because they don't have to all go? That's true, that's a completely
rabbinic context. But right, completely rabbinic. Biblically, you could not have part
of something being טמא. tamei. And I think, and my second just,
you know, I don't know if there's a real answer to
this, like what do we say in the העזבה? ha'azava? We don't
say כל העומד לשחיטה כשחוט דמי.
kol ha'omed lishchita k'shachut dami.
I don't know if they do it. Right, right, right. So okay,
you know what? That's a much larger discussion which we cannot address
right here, but and there's many different סוגיות sugyot of that in
ש"ס shas and you know, there's a question if they are even
consistent or so on. Right, right, yeah, so I can't answer that
now.
Yes, the issue about cutting off the handle of the כלי, kli,
if I had always intended to cut off the handle of the
כלי, kli, that's implying that the כלי kli has not been completed.
And therefore it shouldn't become טמא.
tamei. Yeah, that's a good point.
I would say that first of all, it's a difference between metal
and non-metal vessels, if you remember, actually that was an earlier in
חולין, chulin, that by, that by, oh actually right, by metal vessels
it depends more on your intent to finish it or not. By
non-metal vessels it's more if it's functional or not, so that's part
of the answer. And the other answer is that it might have
been completed. This has been being sold for, you inherited your aunt,
you know, your
aunt's wonderful long-handled frying pan, it's just as some gourmet chef and
that worked for her and it doesn't work for you and you
want to cut it off. So it doesn't mean that it was
not completed, it just means you want to modify it. But alright.
Okay. So that is the end of this סוגיא sugya about how
the arm is considered separate so that it can transmit the טומאה.
tumah. Now we go on, וחכמים אומרים מגע טריפה שחוטה, ve-chachamim omrim
maga tereifa shechuta, the rabbis say the arm is not a נבילה,
neveila, it's a טריפה, tereifa, the act of שחיטה shechita applied to
it, it just didn't work.
And therefore if it's only a טריפה, tereifa, it doesn't really create
טומאה, tumah, so the גמרא gemara says so then why did you
say it's like you touched a טריפה tereifa which implies there is
some טומאה? tumah? So the גמרא gemara says טריפה שחוטה מי מטמיא?
tereifa shechuta mi metameia? What type of טומאה tumah exists by a
טריפה? tereifa? There's no טומאה tumah by a טריפה, tereifa, that's the
whole end of the משנה. mishna.
So rather than saying that's what the משנה mishna means, it's like
you touched a טריפה tereifa and it's nothing, the sense is that
it's like you touched a טריפה tereifa and there's some degree of
טומאה. tumah. So it says אם כן, im ken, yes, כדאבוה דשמואל
k'davuh d'shmuel like the father of Shmuel, דאמר אבוה דשמואל d'amar avuh
d'shmuel the father of Shmuel says, טריפה ששחטה מטמא במקדש, tereifa she-shachata
metamei bamukdash, that
although we normally say there's no טומאה tumah by טריפה, tereifa, there
was a rabbinic טומאה tumah at least that if it touches sacrifices
and sanctified objects, then at least it creates some form of a
rabbinic טומאה. tumah. Okay, so yes, the משנה mishna is saying rather
than just saying it's טהור, tahor, it says it touched a טריפה
שחוטה tereifa shechuta because maybe there's some small level of rabbinic טומאה.
tumah. But the basic point is biblically it's the limb is a
טריפה tereifa and it doesn't create טומאה. tumah. Okay, so now let's
take a look. Now we go on to that basic question about,
oh I'm sorry, so now the גמרא gemara quotes a ברייתא braita
that elaborates on the debate between רבי מאיר rabbi meir and וחכמים
ve-chachamim about the status of the limb. Let's take a look. תניא,
tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, אמר להם רבי מאיר, amar
lahem rabbi meir, so Rabbi Meir said to the sages, וכי מי
טהרו לאבר זה מידי
נבלה? vechi mi tiharuhu l'eiver zeh midei neveilah? What, on what basis
are you, you the sages, saying that this limb is not a
נבילה, neveila, who purified it from being a נבילה? neveila? שחיטת אמו.
shechitat imo.
You're saying that the שחיטה shechita that was done to the mother
applied to the limb, and therefore it's not a נבילה. neveila. That's
what you the sages say, says Rabbi Meir. So he says אם
כן, im ken, if you really think the שחיטה shechita of the
mother applied to the limb, תתירנו באכילה, tatirenu b'achila, why not eat
the limb? Right, how can you say the שחיטה shechita applied to
the limb but the limb isn't kosher? The fact that the limb
isn't kosher means the שחיטה shechita does not apply to it. So
אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to him, no, הרבה מצינו
שאינו גופא יתר מגופא. harbei matzinu she-eino gufa yater mi-gufa.
Many things protect on things that are not its body more than
its body. שהרי שנינו, sheharei shaninu, here's an example. חותך מן העובר
שבמעיה מותר באכילה, chotech min ha-ubar she-be-me-eha mutar b'achila, מן הטחול מן
הכליות אסור באכילה. min ha-tchol min ha-klayot assur b'achila.
Right, one of the first משנה mishna this פרק, perek, if you
dismember the fetus inside of the mother and you שחט shachat the
mother, you can eat the dismembered fetus. If you cut off the
spleen or the kidney and you שחט shachat the mother, you cannot
eat the spleen or the kidney. So what do you see? It's
really ironic. Some things that Something that was more part of the
mother, right, and now it's cut off, the שחיטה shechita of the
mother does not help for it. Something that was a little bit
less part of the mother, the fetus that's cut into pieces, the
שחיטה shechita of the mother does help for. Now that there's a
certain logic to that, right, because the fetus from the very beginning
was not an integral part of the mother, and we were saying
that the שחיטה shechita of the mother works for it, then to
some degree even if you cut it up, like, you haven't really
changed its status so—obviously you have, it's no longer alive, it's no
longer being nurtured by the mother—but nevertheless you were never claiming that
it was an integral part of the mother. So you can even
as cut up you can say while it's in the mother's womb,
the שחיטה shechita of the mother works for it. Whereas the inner
organs which were already which were an integral part of the mother,
once they are detached, right, then the שחיטה shechita of the mother
does not work for it. So they say look, it's possible that
שחיטה shechita can work for something even more if it's not fully
part of the mother than if it was than if it is
fully part of the mother. Okay, so that's their response. Now the
point is the response was not really directly addressed to the challenge.
The challenge is, does the שחיטה shechita apply to the limb or
not? If it applies to the limb, eat the limb. If it
doesn't apply to the limb, then it's a נבלה. neveila. Their answer
was about a case where the שחיטה shechita worked for the cut-up
fetus and that that you could eat it. It wasn't really directly
responsive. Non-responsive. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to say that.
The גמרא Gemara is going to say actually we should have leapfrogged
over part of the exchange. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי קאמר? mai ka’amar? What are they saying? I
mean, it's a good point, but it's not directly responsive to Rabbi
Meir's challenge. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא ואמרי לה כדי,
Amar Rava ve’amrei la kadi, so Rava says and some just say
it was sort of said anonymously, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chisorei mechasra
vehachi katani.
No, the this exchange is missing some words and here's how it
has to be—meaning it was somewhat elliptical and here's how it has
to be taught. אמר להם Amar lahem Rabbi Meir, וכי מתיר לאיבר
זה מידי נבלה? vechi matir le’eivar zeh midei neveila? So now we're
going to restate it again but fill in the blanks. So Rabbi
Meir said, who purified this limb from being a נבלה? neveila? How
could you claim it's not a נבלה? neveila? שחיטת אמו, Shechitas imo,
you say the שחיטה shechita of the mother applies to it and
it's not a נבלה. neveila. אם כן תתירנו באכילה, Im kein tatirenu
ba’achila,
if that were true, then why not eat the limb if the
שחיטה shechita applies to it? אמרו לו, Amru lo, so they said
back to him, which is really filling in from our משנה, mishna,
טרפה
תוכיח, treifa tochiach, no, there times שחיטה shechita works on something, applies
to something, but isn't effective, but is enough to make it not
a נבלה. neveila. Consider a טרפה. treifa. טרפה treifa will prove the
case. ששחיטתה מטהרתה מידי נבלה, She’shechitatah metartah midei neveila,
the שחיטה shechita of an animal that's a טרפה treifa takes it
out of the category of being a נבלה, neveila, ואינה
מתירתה באכילה, ve’eina matiratah ba’achila, does not make it able to be
eaten. So the rabbis say no problem, we have a category of
טרפה, treifa, which is a category of an act of שחיטה shechita
was done but it was not effective, and that means that the
thing can't be eaten but still is not a נבלה. neveila. That's
exactly by טרפה. treifa. So that's what we're going to say is
going on with the limb. You said why not eat the limb?
It's just like a טרפה, treifa, the act of שחיטה shechita was
done to it so it's not a נבלה, neveila, but it wasn't
effective and therefore it cannot be eaten. Okay, which is exactly what
they respond in the משנה. mishna. So now, אמר להם, amar lahem,
Rabbi Meir says back to them, and this is also what he
says back in the משנה, mishna, לא, lo, I don't buy that
analogy. אם טיהרה שחיטת טרפה אותה, Im tihara shechitas treifa osah,
I understand that the שחיטה shechita of a טרפה treifa can make
it no longer a נבלה neveila even though it doesn't make it
מותר muttar to eat. Why? דבר שהיא גופה, Davar she’hi gufah, because
the שחיטה shechita was done to the very animal itself. So obviously
there the act of שחיטה shechita was really done to the animal
that's a טרפה. treifa. That I buy. But תטהר את האיבר דבר
שאינה גופה? titaher es ha’eivar davar she’eina gufah? I don't buy it
by the limb. Don't tell me the שחיטה shechita was done to
the limb, it just wasn't effective. The whole issue of the limb,
the whole reason it wasn't effective, he could be saying, is because
we don't consider it part of the mother or part of the
fetus. So therefore if it's not considered part of the mother and
part of the fetus, the שחיטה shechita wasn't done to it at
all. So he said you're telling me the שחיטה shechita was done
but it wasn't effective? No, by a טרפה treifa I can say
that, obviously the שחיטה shechita was done to the animal and it
wasn't effective because the animal was a טרפה. treifa. But by the
limb, why was the שחיטה shechita not effective? Only because we're saying
the limb is no longer part of the animal. And we're saying
it's not part, and therefore once you're saying that then the שחיטה
shechita wasn't done to the limb. It's not considered part of the
animal to which the שחיטה shechita was done. That's his response. And
by the way, that's where our משנה mishna ends. The rabbis don't
have a response back in our משנה. mishna. So the ברייתא braisa
now fills in what their response would be. Okay, and that's where
they're saying some things are not part of the body and שחיטה
shechita still applies to it. Okay, so אמרו לו, amru lo, and
now here's where the ברייתא braisa kicks in. They said back to
him, הרבה מצאנו שאינה גופה יוצא מגופה, harbeh matza’nu she’eina gufah yotzei
mi’gufah, sometimes שחיטה shechita works even better for something that was is
not part of the body than something that is part of the
body. What's the case? שהרי שנינו, חותך מן העובר שבמעיה מותר באכילה,
sheharei shaninu choteich min haubar shebime'ah mutar b'achilah, if the fetus has
been dismembered inside of the mother cow, the שחיטה shechita works for
it, even though that started off as being less. intrinsic part of
the body. מן הטחול ומן הכליות Min hat'chol u'min haklayot אסור באכילה,
assur b'achilah, but if you cut off the spleen or the kidney
and leave it in the cavity, שחיטה shechitah doesn't work for it.
So he said actually שחיטה shechitah sometimes can work for things that
are not part of the body, sometimes even better than for things
that are part of the body. Now, not exactly because there it
doesn't work for the spleen and the kidney because they're no longer
part of the body at the time you get to the שחיטה,
shechitah, they've been dismembered and they're not part of the body. But
he basically is arguing and this is really the quite conceptual question,
right? Does שחיטה shechitah work for the fetus? When we say שחיטה
shechitah works for the fetus, this really does go back to that
first משנה. mishnah. Are we saying it's because עובר ירך אמו, ubar
yerech imo, it is part of the body? Or are we saying
by the fetus that, you know what, it's not part of the
body, but the fact that it's still, you know, being nurtured by
the mother and grows inside the mother or whatever, that's enough that
the שחיטה shechitah of the mother works for it? So in a
way, what, you know, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir sort of assumes the
first part. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, why does the שחיטה shechitah
work for the fetus? Because it's part of the body. So if
it's not working for the limb, the only way to explain why
it's not working for the limb that's stuck out is because we're
saying it's no longer part of the body. If that's what we're
saying, then it's a נבלה, neveilah, then the שחיטה shechitah didn't apply
to it at all. The sages are saying, no, no, you don't
have to say the fetus was part of the body and you
don't have to say שחיטה shechitah only works for things that are
part of the body. You can say שחיטה shechitah works for things
that are connected to the mother, even if, you know, in some
way, even if they're not part of the body itself. And therefore
it worked for the fetus even though we're not claiming it's fully
a part of the mother. The proof being that even when you
dismember it, the שחיטה shechitah still works, different than even the spleen
and the kidney. So you see it's not really a fully part
of the mother but שחיטה shechitah still works for it. And therefore
even when the limb is sticking out, we can say that even
though it's not that, we don't have to claim it's fully a
part of the mother for the שחיטה shechitah to work, and for
the שחיטה shechitah to relate to it. As long as it is
somewhat connected to the mother, right, then the שחיטה shechitah relates to
it. And in this case because it's sticking out, it wasn't effective.
But still the שחיטה shechitah related to it and therefore it's a
טרפה treifah and not a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, so in the end
this is, you know, it's a very sort of nice conceptual debate
here that, first of all, to make it clear, a nice way
of articulating the difference between נבלה neveilah and טרפה. treifah. נבלה, neveilah,
no שחיטה shechitah was done. טרפה, treifah, שחיטה shechitah was done but
it wasn't halachically effective, okay. In the טרפה treifah obviously because of
the separate problem, טרפה. treifah. By the fetus, the question is what
is the problem. Okay, and the question about the fetus, the arm
stuck out, do we say that it wasn't done to the arm
or it was but wasn't effective? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the
only reason it wasn't effective is because the arm is not considered
part of the body. The rabbis say maybe there's a different reason
it wasn't effective, you know, maybe the פסוק pasuk בשר בשדה טרפה,
basar basadeh tereifah, some other problem it wasn't effective. And anyway, who
says that for שחיטה shechitah to relate to something it has to
be considered an intrinsic part of the body? Maybe even if it's
somewhat loosely connected, שחיטה shechitah can relate to it. And therefore at
least the act of שחיטה shechitah did apply to the limb even
though it wasn't effective, and therefore it's a טרפה treifah not a
נבלה. neveilah. Yes.
So why wouldn't you just say the limb sticking out is loosely
part of the body and therefore it's not only effective but permitted?
That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir asks. That's right. So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says make up your mind.
The response to him is very interesting.
So, right, I mean, the point is as long as you say
that it works. Right. The rabbis never articulate why it doesn't work.
So that's why I threw in the פסוק pasuk of בשר בשדה
טרפה. basar basadeh tereifah. That, and in a way, right, remember that's
what we discussed later by the limb sticking out. Right, if you
think that there's a separate verse בשר בשדה טרפה, basar basadeh tereifah,
you could say, okay, it's still all connected and still all part,
but because it went offside, right, it went, you know, therefore, right,
if somebody goes offside they're still part of the team, they're just
whatever disqualified. So it went offside, doesn't mean you're not related at
all, but you're invalid. That's what the rabbis could say. Whereas רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir could say it's not based on בשר בשדה טרפה.
basar basadeh tereifah. Remember when we learned it, maybe it's based on
a concept of יש לידה לאברים, yesh leidah l'evarim, maybe it's like
it's already born, which makes it consider conceptually separate. Or maybe he
says, without using that phrase at all, the only reason it doesn't
work on the limb is because the limb at this stage is
no longer part of the body. And for that very reason the
שחיטה shechitah doesn't relate to the limb at all. So you're right,
their very debate could be what is the problem with the stuck
out limb. Is the problem that it's no longer part of the
body, which is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says? Or is the
problem, no, it is part of the body, there's some separate problem
like it's offside, and that's the problem. Okay. So now, all right,
so that was pretty, you know, that required holding up but I'm
glad you all stayed with me. And now let's, now we move
on a little bit. So let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי.
Tanya nami hachi. We taught similarly. אמר להן רבי מאיר. Amar lahen
Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says to the sages, וכי
מי טיהרו לאבר זה מידי נבלה? ve'chi mi tiharo l'eivar zeh midei
neveilah? What makes this limb, according to you, not a נבלה? neveilah?
אמרו לו. Amru lo. So rather than having him saying it rhetorically,
he actually said it as a real question.
And they said back, שחיטת אמו. shechitat imo. The שחיטה shechitah of
the mother applies to the limb and therefore it's not a נבלה.
neveilah. אם כן. Im ken. So says he back to them, if
so, תתירהו באכילה. titeerehu b'achilah. Why not allow it to be eaten?
Right, exactly as Charlie said. You know, so still, okay, so שחיטה
shechitah applies, eat it. אמרו לו. Amru lo. So they said to
him without saying why not, they just said there are cases like
this where things שחיטה shechitah applies. But they don't become permitted. טרפה
תוכיח, Treifah tochich, I'll give you an example of טרפה, treifah, ששחיטתה
מטהרתה מידי נבילה, she'shechitatah metaheratah miydei neveilah, the שחיטה shechitah makes it
no longer נבילה, neveilah, ואינה מתירתה באכילה, v'einah matiratah b'achilah, but it
does not make it permissible. So again, without saying what the problem
is with the limb, they say, this is not an unusual case.
We have things that a שחיטה shechitah is considered to have been
done to it, and nevertheless it can't be eaten. So here too
the שחיטה shechitah was done to the limb, there's some other reason
the limb cannot be eaten. So אמר להן, amar lahen, he said
back to them, אם טיהרת שחיטת טרפה אותה, im tiharta shechitata treifa
otah, that's אבר המדולדל בה, aver hameduldal bah, דבר שהוא גופה, davar
shehu gufah, I understand that the שחיטה shechitah of the mother can
work for it and even for a hanging limb, that's new, I'll
get back to that in a minute, let's just finish the thought,
because that's part of the body itself. That I accept that the
שחיטה shechitah applies to the mother even if it's a טרפה. treifah.
But לטהר את העובר שאינה גופה, letaher et haubar she'eina gufah, on
what basis can it work for the fetus which is not part
of the body. Now it's actually interesting here because he says העובר,
haubar, which really Rebbi Meir agrees that the שחיטה shechitah works on
the fetus, it really should have been on the אבר, aver, which
he's considering not part of the body. Anyway, it almost is sort
of framed in a way that's sort of giving them the, you
know, sort of, you know, it's a sending giving them a softball,
because yes, how could it work for the עובר? ubar? Oh, of
course we know it does work for the עובר, ubar, but the
real question is how could it work for the אבר? aver? Okay,
one minute, okay, so anyway, so they say, so again we have
Rebbi Meir saying look, the שחיטה shechitah applies to the animal that
was slaughtered. This limb is not slaughtered, is not part of the
mother, the שחיטה shechitah doesn't apply to it.
So אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to him, הרבה מצאנו
על שאינו גופה יוצא מגופה, harbe matza'nu al she'eino gufah yotzei migufo,
no, there שחיטה shechitah can sometimes work even on things that are
not part of the body, even more than the body. שהרי שנינו
She’harei shaninu, חותך מן העובר שבמעיה מותר באכילה, choteich min ha’ubar she’be’me’eha
mutar ba’achila, if he dismembers a fetus in the womb and slaughters
the mother you can eat it because it was never fully part
of the body. מן הטחול ומן הכליות, min hat'chol u'min haklayot, if
you cut off the kidney or the spleen, אסור באכילה, asur b'achilah,
you cannot eat the kidney and the spleen because those were part
of the body and now they are no longer. So again the
exact same back and forth, just spelled out here in the ברייתא,
braita, what was new that was introduced. So again, Rebbi Meir agrees
to the conceptual category, an act of שחיטה shechitah done to something
that is not permissible to be eaten because it's a טרפה. treifah.
Obviously he agrees to that. The question here is two questions. Number
one is are we prepared to call the limb that's stuck out
part of the body or not? If you don't consider it part
of the body then end of story Rebbi Meir says I can't
say the שחיטה shechitah applied to it. And
the Rabbis say I don't have to call it part of the
body. Actually Rebbi Meir says, excuse me, it's not part of the
body and that's why the שחיטה shechitah doesn't apply to it, so
there was no שחיטה shechitah done. The Rabbis might be saying the
שחיטה shechitah could apply to something that's even not part of the
body, like the fetus. So as long as it's loosely connected the
שחיטה shechitah applies to it. The other question is what's the problem
with the limb, why can't you eat it? So again here Rebbi
Meir would say the only reason you can't eat it is because
it's not part of the body and that's the reason the שחיטה
shechitah doesn't apply to it and that's why it's a נבילה. neveilah.
And the Rabbis presumably would say no, there's some other reason that
you can't eat it, the same way טרפה treifah is another reason
you can't eat an animal, there's some other reason with this limb,
maybe this verse ובשר בשדה טרפה u'vasar basadeh treifah and therefore the
שחיטה shechitah does apply to it, it's not a נבילה, neveilah, but
because of this other reason, that's why it can't be eaten. Okay,
so that's the back and forth and to get, and it was
repeated a couple of times here. The new idea that we've introduced
is a hanging limb, which we said שחיטה shechitah does work for
and I'll get back to that in a second. There was a
question.
Yeah, hanging like the animals, are these normal births, normal whatever fetuses
or is there like a freakish part that it would have an
extra limb or they some of them were normal whatever
regular four legs
or is it, could they happen to be a freakish type of
that they would want to separate the parts out in?
It doesn't matter. I mean, it doesn't have to be freakish, even
a normal type of a thing. You know, the very fact that
the limb is stuck out means that the שחיטה shechitah of the
mother does not apply to the, does it,
maybe they would consider it like a freak? No, no.
It may be a little freakish that you've got a limb sticking
out and it hasn't been born yet. It's a little bit unusual
that the animal does, you know, right. It's also the, that's why
the משנה mishnah constantly talks about בהמה המקשה לילד, behemah hamakshah leileid,
the animal is having a difficulty giving birth because otherwise the birth
would happen simply and you'd be done. Why are you, why is
there a limb sticking out and you're slaughtering the mother? So maybe
because you're afraid the animal is about to die on you because
it's in childbirth and it's endangered and that's why you've got a
limb sticking out and you're having a hard time solving the problem,
might as well salvage the meat and slaughter the mother. So that,
it is a little unusual case, but I wouldn't call it necessarily
freakish and certainly the animal isn't freakish. Now what we introduce here
is also this idea called אבר המדולדל ever hameduldal and that's going
to come up in a later משנה. mishnah. And that is a
case of not the limb of an animal sticking out, but imagine
you've got an actual a limb of the fetus, but imagine you
actually have a limb of the animal itself, like a, you know,
a part of the bottom part of the foot or some part
that won't make it a טרפה treifah that is, it's hard when
you think about a cow how many limbs are there other than
the legs, but anyway, a finger, you don't even have fingers, right,
you've got hooves. So okay, anyway, you've got some type of a
thing, an ear maybe, I don't know. Anyway, some part of the
leg that would not make it a what? Tail. Tail. Anyway, or
a anyway, it's it's it's broken, but it's not fully detached. Okay,
so it's sort of hanging, it's still somewhat by some ligament still
connected, but it's mostly detached and it's still hanging off and it's
still but it's still sort of it's there and it's hanging. Now,
the one question is what is it אבר מן החי? ever min
hachai? Right? At what stage is it אבר מן החי? ever min
hachai? Until it's fully detached, it's not אבר מן החי. ever min
hachai. Okay, but now you have a question of okay, that's fine.
But now I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to שחט
shecht the cow with this hanging limb. And now the question is
what is the status of this limb? And there's two questions. One
is when the cow was שחט shechted or died, did the fact
that now it's died somehow make it as if the limb fell
off, which is an interesting concept, and therefore in that process became
an אבר מן החי? ever min hachai? It's a little strange because
actually while it's dying, it becomes אבר מן החי, ever min hachai,
but there is an opinion about that in the גמרא Gemara which
is called מיתה עושה ניפול. misa ose nipul. Death makes it like
be as if it's finished falling off. Okay, so if it died
naturally, then we actually say it's ironic because we're saying it's אבר
מן החי ever min hachai and we're saying it happens when it
dies, but as it's dying, it's like it's like this limb, you
know, is in the process of falling off, finished, and it's an
אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. That's one question, which is a
little strange. But let's assume not that way or let's assume that
that's only when it dies, might be only when it dies naturally.
When you שחט shecht it, we're not going to say it. You're
still going to have the same question that we have here by
the fetus with the legs sticking out. Okay, fine, the limb is
not אבר מן החי ever min hachai yet because it's still somewhat
attached, but it's not fully attached. So it's almost like this idea.
Is it integrally part of the mother? No. Is it completely detached?
No. It's not אבר מן החי ever min hachai yet, that would
have to be completely detached. So if it's in this sort of,
you know, gray zone, does the שחיטה shechita of the mother apply
to this limb? And now admittedly the limb isn't אבר מן החי,
ever min hachai, but is it כשר? kosher? Is it a טריפה?
treifa? Is it a נבלה? nevela? Just like the question of the
limb of the fetus that is still sticking out. So that's what
we're going to discuss right here. You had a question?
What's the difference between אבר מן החי ever min hachai and נבלה?
nevela?
They're both אסור. assur. אבר מן החי ever min hachai is אסור
לבני נח. assur livnei Noach. They both cause טומאה, tuma, it's a
little difference of the טומאה tuma of אבר מן החי, ever min
hachai, it's a good point.
A נבלה nevela only even a כזית kezayis of meat of the
נבלה nevela causes טומאה. tuma. אבר מן החי ever min hachai only
causes if you remove a כזית kezayis of meat from a limb
of an אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, it doesn't cause טומאה
tuma because it's no longer an אבר. ever. By נבלה, nevela, the
concept is בשר נבלה basar nevela it causes טומאה. tuma. By an
אבר, ever, it's the אבר ever itself, so it has to have
the bone and other forms of it. So if you just remove
a כזית kezayis of the meat, it doesn't cause טומאה. tuma. So
there are two differences: one, the טומאה, tuma, certain kinds will will
cause טומאה tuma as a נבלה nevela not as אבר מן החי,
ever min hachai, and other also אבר מן החי ever min hachai
is forbidden to בני נח. bnei Noach. Okay, but often there's a
lot of overlap. Okay, so let's take a look. Now we move
from the limbs of a fetus to dangling limbs. All right, so
let's take a look.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, כמחלוקת בעוברין כך מחלוקת באיברין. kemachlokes
be'ubarin kach machlokes be'evarin.
The same way there's a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים Chachamim by fetuses with their arms stuck out, there's a
debate by dangling limbs. It doesn't say dangling limbs, but it says
limbs, but that's the context. ורבי יוחנן אמר, V'Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, מחלוקת באבר דעובר. machlokes be'ever de'ubar. The debate
is by the limb of the fetus. Okay, that's as we know,
as we've been talking about, whether it's a נבלה nevela or טריפה.
treifa. אבל באבר דבהמה, aval be'ever de'behema, when it's a dangling limb
of a בהמה, behema, דברי הכל שחיטה עושה ניפול. divrei hakol shechita
ose nipul. Now he's actually saying that this is more strict. Everybody
would agree, even the sages that say that the שחיטה shechita by
the limb of the fetus somewhat works and makes it a טריפה,
treifa, not a נבלה, nevela, everybody would agree that the שחיטה shechita
by an animal with a dangling limb makes it like the limb
fell off and makes it an אבר מן החי, ever min hachai,
which is a strange idea. But remember, it is dangling. Okay, by
the fetus it might have been out of the womb, but it
wasn't dangling. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is actually going to reverse
that. Okay, what?
דברי הכל?
Divrei hakol?
דברי הכל, Divrei hakol, meaning even the sages that say that the
שחיטה shechita by the fetus somewhat applies, here they would say the
שחיטה shechita has no relevance to the dangling limb because again, it
was dangling, it was in the process of falling off. The גמרא
Gemara is going to reverse this. The גמרא Gemara is going to
say the dangling limb is better than the fetus case, which makes
sense because it's more intrinsically part of the animal. But for now
we're suggesting... It's worse, presumably because it was dangling. Okay, so let's
take a look. אמר רב יוסף בר חנינא, Amar Rav Yosef bar
Chanina, מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן, mai taama de-Rabbi Yochanan, what is the
reasoning of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that he says the sages agree
by the dangling limb? So אליבא דרבנן, aliba de-rabbanan, so he says
הא איתא תקנתא בחזרה והא ליתא תקנתא בחזרה. ha isei takanta be-chazara
ve-ha leisei takanta be-chazara. So rather than what I was saying, which
is the limb was dangling and more detached, it says another thing,
which is even better. The fetus could always pull its arm back
in. Now if you remember, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was of the
opinion, it was debated at the beginning of the פרק, perek, that
if the fetus pulled its arm back in, it would become permissible.
It doesn't remain forbidden and you שוחט shecht the mother, now you
can even eat the limb. So he says with the limb sticking
out, there the sages are saying it's still in the פרשה שחיטה
parsha shechita because that limb could be pulled back and could actually
be permissible to be eaten. Whereas the dangling limb, that will never
become permissible again, and therefore, you know, therefore the rabbis would say
that the שחיטה shechita does not apply to it. מתיבי, Meitvei, the
גמרא Gemara says, let me challenge this. אמר להם רבי מאיר. Amar
lahem Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said to the rabbis,
right in the back and forth we just quoted. לא אם אמרתם
בשחיטת טרפה שתהא שחיטת טרפה אותה ובאבר המדולדל בה, lo im amartem
shechitat treifa she-tehei shechitat treifa otah u-ve-ever meduldal bah, that was the
last ברייתא baraita where the limb thing was introduced. If you say
the שחיטה shechita of the טרפה treifa that works for it and
for the dangling limb, דבר שבגופה davar she-begufah because it's part of
the same body. תטהר לעובר דבר שאינה גופה, titaher le-ubar davar she-einah
gufah, how could it work for the limb of the fetus which
isn't part of the body? Now here it sounds like the exact
opposite of what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. It says even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir will grant that the שחיטה shechita will work for
the dangling limb, that the dangling limb is better than the case
of the fetus. Okay, so that seems to be a real problem.
It's even a problem on ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because he said
they also debate the dangling limb.
So גמרא Gemara asks, what is dangling?
Dangling means no, not atrophied, like it's severed but not completely severed.
Okay, if it was ripped, you could imagine maybe it was attacked
by an animal?
We had a cat with a broken tail. And it was kind
of floppy.
Okay, so that would be an example, right. I mean you could
imagine that it was attacked by some, by a cougar or something
like that, and it tore at the limb and there's still some
ligament holding it on, but it's 90 percent, you know, detached. So
that's the case.
It's again hard to imagine how that happens without it being a
טרפה treifa because pretty much the only limbs you have access to
are the legs and maybe the tail, and the legs are, and
you know, and pretty much I mean, and unless you're really low
in the leg, anywhere like from the, you know, from the bottom
knee up makes it a טרפה. treifa. So, you know, again it's
hard to imagine what the case would be. But anyway, the animal
טרפה treifa
or the leg טרפה? treifa? No, the animal. If the leg is
at a certain point is broken, then the animal becomes a טרפה.
treifa. Okay. So now the, so anyway from this it seems like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was willing to grant that the שחיטה shechita
works by the dangling limb, which is against both ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan because both of them said that
the dangling limb was debated. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that even
the חכמים chachamim even agree to that case. So let's take a
look. בשלמא לרבי שמעון בן לקיש Bishlama le-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish for
the top of ע"ג עמוד ב', ayin gimmel amud bet, it works
according to רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, I can
deal with it. לדבריכם קאמר, Le-divreichem ka-amar, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could
be saying back to the rabbis, even according to you. לדידי, Lidi,
as far as I'm concerned, לא שנא אבר דעובר ולא שנא אבר
דבהמה כי הדדי נינהו. lo shna ever de-ubar ve-lo shna ever de-behema
kiyadadi ninhu. Whether it's the limb of the fetus that's sticking out
or whether it's the dangling limb of the בהמה, behema, as far
as the animal, as far as I'm concerned they're the same and
the שחיטה shechita doesn't work for it and it's a נבילה. neveila.
That's my position. אלא, Ella,
but it doesn't say has the end. But according to you, I'll
grant you that maybe I could see your point by the dangling
limb. I don't agree to you by the dangling limb, but I
might be able to see your point there because at least it's
part of the animal, but I can't see your point by the
limb of the fetus. That's how it would work with ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, that they could be debating the dangling limb, but רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir sort of saying, I could even see the point
of the dangling limb but I don't see it by the fetus.
אלא לרבי יוחנן, Ella le-Rabbi Yochanan, but according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, קשיא, kashya, this doesn't make any sense, because why is רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir saying the שחיטה shechita works for the dangling limb
if even the rabbis agree that it doesn't work in that case?
אלא, Ella, you're right, the גמרא Gemara says. It's the opposite. אתמר,
Itmar, if it was said that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says they
agree, הכי אתמר. hachi itmar. It was, this is how it was
said: they agree the opposite way. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, כמחלוקת בעוברים כך מחלוקת באברים. kemachloket be-ubarim kach
machloket be-evarim. Like we said before, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says the
same way they debate by the limb of the fetus, they debate
the dangling limb, whether the שחיטה shechita works for it or not.
ורבי יוחנן אמר, Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says,
no, מחלוקת באבר דעובר, machloket be-ever de-ubar, they only debate the limb
of the fetus. אבל באבר דבהמה, Aval be-ever de-behema, when it comes
to the dangling limb of the בהמה, behema, דברי הכל אין שחיטה
עושה ניבול, divrei hakol ein shechita osa nibul, everybody would agree that
the שחיטה shechita does not make it like it fell off and
that the שחיטה shechita really is effective for it. Okay, and might
be, now the question is how effective is it? Effective that it's
a טרפה, treifa, or even effective that you could actually eat it?
Okay, but that's not clear, but at least everybody would agree that
the שחיטה shechita relates to the dangling limb, and that makes sense
because that's exactly what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says, I understand why, and I even agree to you in
the case of a dangling limb because at least that's part of
the actual body of the בהמה behema itself, right? But how... How
can you, but I can't agree to you in the case of
the limb of the fetus, that's not part of the body. Okay,
so that really does fit in the language of the ברייתא Braita
that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir agrees to the case of the dangling
limb. Okay, and if by the way if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, אין שחיטה עושה ניפול, ein shechita osa nipul, like six lines
down in the narrow lines, רש"י Rashi just clarifies, דטהור מלטמא אף
על פי שאסור באכילה. detahor miltame af al pi she-assur beachila. It
would be exactly what the Rabbis were saying by the limb of
the fetus. The שחיטה shechita applies to it, so it's not a
נבילה, neveila, it's a טריפה, treifa, but because it's not really fully
attached to the animal, it's dangling, you can't eat it. So now
we actually have it very nice, right according to רבי יוחנן. Rebbi
Yochanan. Here's a case that everybody agrees is like what the Rabbis
say by the limb of the fetus. The dangling limb, because it's
part of the animal the שחיטה shechita applies to it, so it's
not a נבילה, neveila, but it's a טריפה, treifa, but for some
reason because it's dangling we don't even know what the problem is
with dangling, if it's enough that the שחיטה shechita applies why not
eat it? We'll see that later. But for some reason because it's
in this gray zone, semi-attached semi-detached,
it's the שחיטה shechita applies but it doesn't make it kosher, so
it's like a טריפה, treifa, it's not טמא tamei but you can't
eat it. And the Rabbis say that's exactly what we say by
the limb of the fetus, right, is that if it's in this
gray zone, semi-attached semi-not whatever, the שחיטה shechita applies to it, it's
not a טריפה treifa but you can't eat it. And רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says give me a break, the dangling limb is part
of the animal itself, so there I can admit to it. The
fetus, the limb, that's already not part of the animal and that
should be a נבילה. neveila. Okay, so let's take a look now
at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי יוסף בר חנינא מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן אליבא
דרבי מאיר, Amar Rebbi Yosef bar Chanina mai ta'ama d'Rebbi Yochanan aliba
d'Rebbi Meir, okay, so we just really said this, why does רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan now say that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir will concede
the point of the dangling limb, that the שחיטה shechita applies to
it, so for the exact reason that was in the ברייתא, Braita,
האי גופא והאי לאו גופא, hai gufa ve-hai lav gufa, the dangling
limb is at least part of the animal itself, so there he'll
agree the שחיטה shechita applies to it even though you can't eat
it, but not by the limb of the fetus which is not
part of the animal itself.
Okay, now that we've talked about the שחיטה shechita and does the
שחיטה shechita apply and make it to be at least a non-נבילה,
neveila, now we're going to talk about what happens if the animal
just naturally dies and it has this dangling limb. Let's take a
look. אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav Yitzchak
bar Yosef amar Rebbi Yochanan, so רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak
bar Yosef says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, הכל
מודים, hakol modim, everybody agrees, whether רב מאיר Reb Meir and the
חכמים Chachamim and whatever they say when you שחט shacht the animal
with the dangling limb, everybody agrees שמיתה עושה ניפול ואין שחיטה עושה
ניפול, she-mita osa nipul ve-ein shechita osa nipul, that death makes falling
and שחיטה shechita does not make falling. So עושה ניפול osa nipul
means that in the act of dying it's like the limb finished
falling off, okay, which again is a little ironic but that's what
we say, and therefore if it dies naturally the limb becomes an
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai because it's like in the process
of dying, you know if the animal's dying what sort of died
first is this thing that's already half dead, this dangling limb, it's
like it fell off and it's an אבר מן החי. eiver min
hachai. So everybody agrees that when it dies naturally the limb becomes
an אבר מן החי eiver min hachai and everybody agrees when you
שחט shacht it that it's not a problem, at least it's not
a נבילה, neveila, it's a טריפה treifa like we said before. Okay,
so let's take a look.
במאי עסקינן, be-mai askinan, what are we talking about? אילימא באבר דעובר,
ilima be-eiver d'ubar, if you're talking about not the dangling limb but
the limb of the fetus, מיפלג פליגי, miflag pligi, you can't say
they agree that when you do the שחיטה shechita it works, that's
exactly the case they debate is the limb of the fetus. אלא
באבר דבהמה, ela be-eiver d'behema, we're talking about the dangling limb
of the animal itself. מיתה תנינא שחיטה תנינא, mita tanina shechita tanina,
so what חידוש chiddush are you telling me? We both have a
משנה Mishna that tells me when it dies it becomes an אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai and we have a משנה Mishna that
tells me that when you שחט shacht it it's okay. Where do
we have this? מיתה תנינא, mita tanina, we've taught the case of
when the animal dies naturally the limb becomes an אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, because here's what the משנה Mishna says, this is
way if you look at the side you might expect this to
be coming up in like a משנה Mishna later in this פרק
perek because it fits into everything we're talking about, וקמן קכ"ז עמוד
ב', vekaman kof chaf zayin amud bet, so this is about another
sixty דף daf or whatever fifty דף daf ahead of where we
are. So this whole thing comes up way at the end. Okay,
anyway, מה? קמ"ב? kamav?
Just in case you thought that we were going to get through
this and not have to talk about these issues ever again, they
will come up again in two months. Okay,
תנינא, tanina, מתה הבהמה, meta habehema, if the animal with the dangling
limb dies, הבשר צריך הכשר, habasar tzarich hechshier, the meat of the
animal will not become טמא tamei until it comes in contact with
water, right, you all know this idea that food, whether fruit and
vegetables or whether meat, is not susceptible to become טמא tamei until
it actually comes in contact with water, that's called צריך הכשר. tzarich
hechshier. So this animal with a dangling limb died, the meat will
not be able to become טמא tamei until it comes in contact
with water of the actual animal itself. הבשר צריך הכשר, habasar tzarich
hechshier, where am I? והאבר
מטמא משום אבר מן החי, ve-haeiver metame mishum eiver min hachai, and
the limb causes טומאה tumah because of אבר מן החי. eiver min
hachai. So you see it's explicit in a משנה, Mishna, it's not
debated, that when the animal dies the limb becomes an אבר מן
החי, eiver min hachai, so that's not a חידוש. chiddush. ואינו מטמא
משום אבר מן הנבלה דברי רבי מאיר. ve-eino metame mishum eiver min
haneveila divrei Rebbi Meir. But it does not cause טומאה tumah of
a נבלה, neveilah, and here exactly Dov said, what difference does it
make? If the animal is dead, what do I care if you
call it אבר מן החי eiver min ha-chai or אבר מן הנבלה?
eiver min ha-neveilah? So one difference is, can a בן נח ben
Noach eat it? But here there is a difference even in טומאה.
tumah. The difference in טומאה tumah is, as I said, נבלה neveilah
causes טומאה tumah only by, it says the meat of a נבלה
neveilah causes טומאה, tumah, so a כזית kezayis of the meat causes,
and אבר מן החי eiver min ha-chai it has to be a
whole limb. So if the limb somehow, the meat was separated from
the bone, it would not cause טומאה. tumah. Okay, so here you
see it is clear that when the animal dies, the limb becomes
an אבר מן החי. eiver min ha-chai. That is, so there, that
is already in the משנה. mishna. רבי שמעון אומר לא הוכשרו. Rebbi
Shimon omer lo huchsharu. Now there is a difference of רבי שמעון.
Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says that,
that,
hold on one minute, I
am sorry, oh no, שחיטה נמי, shchita nami, I am sorry, I
jumped ahead, I jumped. That was the end of it, דברי רבי
מאיר. divrei Rebbi Meir. Okay, now, so that is if it dies
naturally. שחיטה נמי, shchita nami, and the fact that when you שחט
shcht it, it works for the dangling limb, that is also in
a משנה. mishna. תנינא, tenina, we taught in the משנה, mishna, נשחטה
הבהמה. nishchata ha-beheimah. So this is basically the same משנה, mishna, if
the בהמה beheimah rather than died was slaughtered with this dangling limb,
הוכשרו בדמיה דברי רבי מאיר. huchsharu be-damahah divrei Rebbi Meir. So רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir says that the blood of the בהמה beheimah that
comes out when you שחט shcht it, that is the liquid that
makes the meat susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. By, when it died
naturally, there was no blood, it died of old age. You slaughtered
it, there was blood. The blood that came out makes the whole
animal susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. That is what רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says. רבי שמעון אומר לא הוכשרו. Rebbi Shimon omer lo huchsharu.
They did not become, blood of שחיטה shchita does not make things
susceptible, that is not a liquid that makes things susceptible. Now where
do you see there that it means that this dangling limb can
be, you know, is, you know, the שחיטה shchita works for it?
Where do you see anything there about the dangling limb? So the
key here is in the ו. vov. It says הוכשרו בדמיה, huchsharu
be-damahah, not הוכשר. huchshar. They have become susceptible. What is the they?
They is the בהמה beheimah and the limb. Now if the limb
were considered to be that the שחיטה shchita did not work for
it and was considered a נבלה, neveilah, you would not have to
say it is susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. It is טמא, tamei,
it is a נבלה. neveilah. So the fact that you say that
it is susceptible means that the limb itself is not טמא, tamei,
that the limb itself is at worst like a טריפה, treifah, not
a נבלה. neveilah. So there you see that everybody agrees in the
case of when you slaughter it, that the dangling limb is not
a נבלה. neveilah. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, I could have
got out of it. אי מהא הוה אמינא, ei mei-ha havah amina,
if I just said that, מאי הוכשרו, mai huchsharu, בשר? basar? What
does it mean they became susceptible? בשר, basar, maybe it just means
the meat of the animal, it is not referring to the dangling
limb. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, הוכשרו קתני. huchsharu ktani. It
says הוכשרו huchsharu in the plural, so clearly it is referring to
the dangling limb, and if the dangling limb had to be susceptible,
then clearly it is not itself a נבלה. neveilah. No, מהו דתימא
חדא בשר הפורש מן הבהמה וחדא בשר הפורש מן האבר, mah de-teima
chada basar haporesh min ha-beheimah ve-chada basar haporesh min ha-eiver, that maybe
no, maybe we are still talking, we are not talking about the
limb itself. We are talking about two types of meat that become
susceptible. One is meat that comes off of, meaning the issue about
the limb, the possible, hold on, let me just check רש"י Rashi
a minute.
Yes, so,
one second, just one second I just got to make sure I
got this straight.
הוה אמינא מאי
הוכשרו בשר, חדא בשר הפורש מן הבהמה וחדא בשר הפורש, havah amina
mai huchsharu basar, chada basar haporesh min ha-beheimah ve-chada basar haporesh, right,
so, just one minute, חדא בשר הפורש מן
הבהמה,
chada basar haporesh min ha-beheimah,
still not
getting,
oh, okay, okay, now I got it, now I got it. Okay,
so the point is like this. The only thing when something separates
from an animal when an animal is alive, there is only a
concept of אבר מן החי. eiver min ha-chai. There is not a
concept of בשר מן החי. basar min ha-chai. If somebody were to
tear a piece of meat off of an animal that is alive,
okay, that animal, I mean it cannot be eaten, there is בשר
מן החי basar min ha-chai in terms of the prohibition of eating
it, but there is not a concept of בשר מן החי basar
min ha-chai in order to cause טומאה. tumah. The only thing that
causes טומאה tumah is an אבר מן החי. eiver min ha-chai. So
what we are trying to argue here is that When the animal
dies and it has this dangling limb, dies naturally, it makes the
dangling limb an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. When you שחט
shecht it, it doesn't make it an אבר מן החי eiver min
hachai and כציר Katzir said that you have to become susceptible. So
that proves that it does not become an אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. So the גמרא Gemara says no, I could have got
out of that. Why? I could have said that even if you
שחט shecht it, if it had a dangling limb, it would become
אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. What's the case here? The case
here is not a case of a dangling limb, the case here's
a case of dangling meat, as it were. Okay? So it's meat
that was actually not a limb, you know, meat that was torn,
that wasn't completely removed. Now if there, the reason there it does
not become, the reason there it does not become טמא tamei is
because it cannot become an אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, it's
not a limb, it's just meat. So that's maybe why the משנה
mishna there I would have got out of it in saying if
it were really a limb, then even when you שחט shecht it,
it's like the limb fell off and it's אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. The reason this משנה mishna says when you שחט shecht
it, it does not become טמא tamei is because we're not talking
about a limb, we're talking about dangling meat. Okay? So that was
obviously a hard read because until now we've all been talking about
dangling limbs, but that's how it just says that I could have
got out of this, had we not said explicitly this law that
when you שחט shecht the limb does not become אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. So let's take a look. והוכשרו קתני זה, vehuchsharu
katani zei, these can become susceptible, which means they themselves are not
טמא, tamei, which means the limb is not טמא tamei when you
שחט shecht the animal. So גמרא Gemara says no, מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, I might have thought, חד לבשר פירש מן הבהמה וחד לבשר
פירש מן האבר, chad lebasar poresh min habehema vechad lebasar poresh min
haeiver, that what זה zei means is whether it is meat that's
coming from the animal, dangling as it were from the animal, or
whether it is meat that is that is coming from the limb,
then in both of those cases it is not אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, it is only בשר מן החי, basar min hachai,
I might have thought in those cases that's what it's referring to
and that's why it's not טמא. tamei. But if it was really
a limb that was dangling, then maybe the שחיטה shechita actually would
have would have made it into אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai.
ומאי אומדי דהאי מהאי, umai umdai dehai mehai, why would I have
needed to say both cases of the meat that is removed from
the animal while the animal is alive and moving, excuse me meat
that is dangling from the animal is one case, and meat that
is removed from the animal after it dies, why would I have
thought there's a difference? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salcha daatach amina, I would
have thought, הואיל ומטמא טומאה חמורה אגב אביו אימא לא ליבעי הכשר
קמשמע לן. ho-il umitamei tumah chamura agav aviv eima lo libaei hechsher
kamashma lan.
So, okay one minute, I'm so sorry I'm just this is a
little complicated and I'm just trying to make sure I got this
straight.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm just it made sense when I prepared
it. I'm just getting a little bit lost now. Hold on one
second. Let me just let me just read רש"י Rashi again, I'm
sorry, hold on. כי אם שאמור בה קודם שחיטה כדתני האבר והבשר
המדלדלין בבהמה. kay ve-im she-amur bah koidem shechita k'deitni haeiver vehabasar hameduldalin
babehema. שפירש מן האבר לאחר שחיטה sheporsh min haeiver le-acher shechita and
ומאי דבשר פירש מן האבר מן הפורש מן הבהמה דאיצריכו
לאיתויינהו.
umai de-basar poresh min haeiver
min haporesh
min habehema de-itzrechu
le-eisuyun.
Okay,
okay, okay, fine. Okay, now I got it. Okay, sorry about that.
Okay, so here's the case. Back to this. We are saying that
you've got a dangling limb, and we are claiming that when it
dies naturally, it's like it fell off and it's אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. That's מפורש meforash in one משנה. mishna. We're also
saying that when you שחט shecht it, it's not like it fell
off and it's not אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, right? That's
the פשט. p'shat. שחיטה shechita is not עושה ניפול. oseh neipul. Now
the question is that's implicit in the משנה. mishna. Because the משנה
mishna says that when you שחט, shecht, they become
they can become susceptible to becoming טמא, tamei, but they themselves are
not טמא. tamei. So it shows you that that limb is not
an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So the משנה mishna says
no, maybe the limb so the גמרא Gemara says no, maybe the
limb is an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. But what it's
saying is not you know what it's saying is not טמא tamei
but is susceptible is if you take took meat off of that
אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. Now remember before I said that
only the אבר eiver as a whole limb causes טומאה. tumah. If
you remove just the flesh from it without the bone, it doesn't
cause טומאה. tumah. So when it says that it needs it's susceptible
but doesn't cause טומאה, tumah, maybe it's not referring to the limb
itself, maybe the limb itself is אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai,
it's like it did fall off, but the thing that is susceptible
but is not טמא tamei is the meat that is removed from
the limb. Okay? And that can that will only become susceptible but
is not טמא tamei itself. So let's read that again.
Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might think, חד לבשר
פירש... chad lebasar poresh... The case of what is susceptible is if
you remove flesh from the limb. That's not טמא tamei as איבר
מן החי, ever min hachai, but that and that would become susceptible.
ומאי אומדא האי מהאי? umai umda hai mehai? So says the גמרא
Gemara why would you have to tell me both of those? Why
would I think there would be any difference? No, סלקא דעתך אמינא,
salka daitach amina, I would have thought הואיל ומטמא טומאה חמורה אגב
אביו, hoil umitamei tumah chamura agav aviv, when you remove flesh from
the limb that's איבר מן החי, ever min hachai, when it was
attached to the איבר מן החי, ever min hachai, it was it
actually was a source of טומאה. tumah. Now that you've removed it
and it's just flesh, it's no longer a source of טומאה. tumah.
But since it started its life as a source of טומאה, tumah,
I might think אימא לא בעי הכשר, eima lo bei hechsher, maybe
now it's susceptible without even coming in contact with water? Right, this
limb, which was an איבר מן החי. ever min hachai. Now you
took meat off of it. Because it's not part of a whole
limb, it's no longer a source of טומאה. tumah. And now this
meat if something טמא tamei touches it is can become טמא. tamei.
Maybe I would think that in this case you don't need water
to come in contact to make it susceptible. If it started its
life as a source of טומאה, tumah, now it's already susceptible to
become טמא tamei even without coming in contact with water. So קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan and it would tell me that's not
the case, it needs to become susceptible. So that's just how I
could have gotten out of that משנה. Mishna. Maybe the משנה Mishna
wouldn't have been talking about a limb, maybe the משנה Mishna would
have been talking about meat removed from the limb. But at the
end of the day, it's pretty clear in the משנה Mishna both
points. Number one, that if you have a dangling limb when the
animal dies, it is this strange idea of מיתה עושה ניפול, misa
osa nipul, that it's like the limb fell off first and it's
an איבר מן החי. ever min hachai. And if you have a
dangling limb and you שחט shacht the mother, then at least even
if you can't eat the limb, and we're going to speak in
a minute why you can't eat that dangling limb, but at least
the שחיטה shechitah makes it so it's not איבר מן החי, ever
min hachai, and it's not נבילה, neveilah, and the שחיטה shechitah did
apply to it and at worst it's like a טריפה. treifa. Okay,
so even at the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the
חכמים Chachamim about the limb stuck out of the of the fetus,
is that a טריפה, treifa, נבילה, neveilah, whatever, by the dangling limb
when you שחט shacht the animal the mother, it's not an איבר
מן החי, ever min hachai, it's not a נבילה, neveilah, the שחיטה
shechitah did apply to it and at worst it's like a טריפה.
treifa. Now the question we still have to say is, if it's
really part of the mother and the שחיטה shechitah worked for it,
why can't you eat it? We already discussed why you can't eat
the limb about the fetus, but why can't you eat this dangling
limb? So that's now what the גמרא Gemara turns to. Let's take
a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so let's just do
these next two lines, נקיט רב יצחק בר יוסף בידך, nekit Rav
Yitzchak bar Yosef beyadecha, take the position of רב יצחק בר יוסף
Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef in your hand, meaning that he said that
everybody agrees that the שחיטה shechitah of the mother makes the limb,
dangling limb, at least you know at least not a נבילה. neveilah.
Why? דתניא דרבה בר בר חנה קאי כוותיה, detanya deRabba bar bar
Chana kai kivateih, because רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana
says the same position. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa,
ובשר בשדה טריפה לא תאכלו, uvasar basadeh treifa lo socheilu,
meat that is in a field don't eat, and remember we talked
about the limb of the fetus out of the womb, להביא את
האיבר, lehavi es haeiver, which is the stuck out limb of the
fetus, ואת הבשר המדולדלין בבהמה ובחיה ובעוף, ve'es habasar hamiduldalin bibeheimah uvichayah
uva'of, and also hanging limbs. So the same idea of ובשר בשדה
טריפה. uvasar basadeh treifa. It is somehow somewhat out of its zone.
It's somewhat detached from the mother. Not fully, but like the limb
of the fetus. And that's why the same reason you can't eat
the limb of the fetus that gets stuck out, you can't eat
the dangling limb. ושחטן, Veshachtan, even if you שחט shacht the mother,
שהן אסורין, shehen asurin, they remain forbidden. And now ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan, and let's just read these five words, אין בהם אלא מצות
פרוש בלבד, ein bahem ela mitzvas peirush bilvad,
this really a thing that you can't eat the dangling limb is
not the same problem as the limb of the fetus that's stuck
out. The limb of the fetus that's stuck out, that's really a
biblical problem, the שחיטה shechitah really did not apply to it, did
not make it כשר, kosher, it's a real serious problem. But a
dangling limb, he says that's only although we quoted a פסוק pasuk
it doesn't really mean it and really it's only like a rabbinic
idea. That's not appropriate to eat this dangling limb when it was
dangling, but technically actually the שחיטה shechitah works fully for the dangling
limb and really according to הלכה halacha you could even eat the
dangling limb. So if you can eat it, certainly it's not an
איבר מן החי, ever min hachai, certainly it's not a נבילה, neveilah,
certainly it's not טמא. tamei. So really the whole dangling limb thing
is a pure rabbinic thing and the real problem is the fetus,
but not the dangling limb.